A Guide to the Papers of R. Samuel Meade, 1866 (1896-1943) 1943
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of R. Samuel Meade, 1866 (1896-1943) 1943
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4337
This collection consists of 620 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift to the Library from Mrs. Olga Trail of American Lake, Washington, on June 6, 1953.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, ca. 620 items, 1896-1943, contains the papers of R. Samuel Meade and his second wife, Alice Exall Meade. Mr. Meade lived and practiced law in Lebanon, Virginia from about 1910 to 1936. During that time he worked as the Russell County Clerk, an U. S. Commissioner for Russell County, a surveyor, and an insurance salesman. Mr. Meade was also a Mason and a churchgoer, and had at least two daughters, Grace and Virginia. Virginia married three times, once to Douglas Exall whom she divorced, then to a Mr. Wolfe who died in a car accident, and then to a Mr. Godsey. Virginia had at least two daughters and she lived, for a time, in Bristol, Tennessee. Meade married Alice Exall, a teacher from Richmond, Virginia, in 1919. She apparently did not move to Lebanon following the wedding, but resided there during the later 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s. Meade was considerably older than Mrs. Meade and was a heavy drinker and ill during much of their marriage; Mrs. Meade spent much of the marriage supporting him either emotionally or financially. During the Depression, Mrs. Meade tried to gain employment to support her husband and herself.
Among the personal correspondence and papers are letters of Alice Exall Meade and her mother, Annie Exall Burbank. There is also a letter, September 4, 1934, from Representative John W. Flannagan, Jr., concerning Alice Meade's inquiry as to a job. There are also papers regarding Alice Meade's involvement with the Work Projects Administration. Miscellaneous papers include poems, satires, and other humorous writings from the era. Mrs. Meade's teaching papers offer a glimpse into education during the early 1900s.
The business and legal papers contain cases which include dockets and legal briefs. There are also two legal writing pads that contain Mr. Meade's notes on cases and accounts. There are also has three ledgers that Meade kept to record Russell County financial information during his clerkship.
Contents List
- Personal Correspondence of R. Samuel Meade and Alice Exall Meade
  - Correspondence of Alice Exall Meade 1896, 1912-1936, n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of R. Samuel Meade 1925-1936 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Postcards 1924-1943 (Box 1)
- Personal Papers of R. Samuel Meade and Alice Exall Meade
  - Advertisements n.d. (Box 1)
  - Car Medallion, Address Book... n.d. (Box 1)
  - Financial Papers of R. Samuel Meade 1918-1921, n.d. (Box 1)
  - House Floor Plans n.d. (Box 1)
  - Invitations, Announcements, and Notices 1907-1935, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Magisterial Districts; Poll tax lists 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - Mason Lodge Papers of R. Samuel Meade 1906-1935 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1919-1934, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Presidential and Governor Campaign Literature 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - Teacher Papers 1917, n.d. (Box 2)
- Business and Legal Correspondence of R. Samuel Meade
  - Correspondence--Official 1910-1936, n.d., 5 folders (Box 2)
- Business and Legal Papers of R. Samuel Meade
  - Blank Forms n.d. (Box 3)
  - Commissioner Financial Settlements 1914-1934 (Box 3)
  - Deeds of Release 1925-1933 (Box 3)
  - Land Surveys, A-Z n.d. (Box 3)
  - Legal Accounts, A-Z n.d. (Box 3)
  - Legal Cases, A-C n.d. (Box 3)
  - Legal Cases, D-G n.d. (Box 3)
  - (Box 3)
  - Legal Cases, H-K n.d. (Box 4)
  - Legal Cases, L-R n.d. (Box 4)
  - Legal Cases, S n.d. (Box 4)
  - Legal Cases, T-Z n.d. (Box 4)
  - Legal Codes 1917-1936, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Legal Tablets n.d. (Box 4)
  - Russell County Clerk Receipts and Records 1894-1926 (Box 4)
  - Russell County Financial Records kept by R. Samuel Meade ca. 1914-1934, Oversize Bound Volumes on 2M (Box 5)
- Bound Volumes
  - Account Book and Record of Indexing Project--Law Order Book for the Work Projects Administration kept by Alice Exall Meade 1939-1942 (Box 5)
    [project to index a law order book--account book and record kept track of hours and wages put into the project]
  - Composition Book; Minutes of a Danville, Virginia debating society 1866, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Grade Book kept by Alice Buckner Exall [Meade] for a school in the Richmond area 1917-1918 (Box 5)